<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris Clarkson</title>
    <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chris Clarkson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 16:52:09 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://chrisclarkson.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaunch</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/posts/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 16:52:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/posts/first/</guid>
      <description>And so, With the help of Hugo the site has been relaunched.
Look out for posts on:
 Hacking Reverse Engineering Electronics Coding The Cloud  There will also be the odd post about Climbing, Motorcycles and other goings on too</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Chris</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/about/</guid>
      <description>Identifies as Developer, Hacker, and Geek. Has a passion for all things tech especially if it is Cyber Security related.
Loves Science Fiction and Fantasy. Favourite books are the Lord of the Rings and books from the Warhammer 40k Universe. Prefers TV Series to Films, Game of Thrones, Walking Dead, Stargate etc. but does enjoy films from the MCU and Star Wars.
Also a keen motorcyclist and boulderer when not chasing around after 2 kids and my darling wife.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/projects/</guid>
      <description>Work I am doing at the moment&amp;hellip;
 VulnHub - To support my PWK/OSCP course and generally sharpen those offensive security skills I have been working through some of the machines on here. HackTheBox - More sharpening of skills, but with challenges to test a particular area as well such as RE, crypto etc.  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/resources/</guid>
      <description> Pages Just some links to pages I have found useful across the internet.
 Pentesterlabs HackTheBox Hacksplaining BrightTalk 0x00sec Azeria Labs CodeArcana Blackroomsec Radare2 Gitbook Cheatography  Github Repos Useful Repos from Github
 Ropper Reverse Engineering JohnTheRipper Ninja Admins Awesome Hacking Awesome CyberSkills  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Study List</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/study/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/study/</guid>
      <description>Here is a list of the materials I have or am studying.
Course  Penetration Testing With Kali (In Progress)  The precursor course to the OSCP examination. Its very difficult to put into words how much I have learned from this course so far, and there is always more to learn #TryHarder.  Certified Ethical Hacker (Completed)  An excellent introduction to the ways a hacker works to compromise a system.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>