<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris Clarkson</title>
    <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chris Clarkson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:30:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://chrisclarkson.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hack The Box</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/others/hackthebox/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/others/hackthebox/</guid>
      <description>HackTheBox - More sharpening of skills, but with challenges to test a particular area as well such as RE, crypto etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Root Me</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/others/root-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:25:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/others/root-me/</guid>
      <description>Root-Me - Wargaming and challenges to practice a wide range of skills</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vulnhub</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/others/vulnhub/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/others/vulnhub/</guid>
      <description>VulnHub - To support my PWK/OSCP course and generally sharpen those offensive security skills I have been working through some of the machines on here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Over The Wire</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/others/overthewire/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/others/overthewire/</guid>
      <description>OverTheWire Wargaming site to practice exploitation skills</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coming Soon</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/tutorials/coming_soon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 16:22:49 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/tutorials/coming_soon/</guid>
      <description>Its always better to give rather than receive, so as time allows I will be writing some tutorials on various topics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/personal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/personal/</guid>
      <description>Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Chris. I am a Hacker, Engineer and Geek. I have a passion for all things Cyber Security, but my main areas of interest are in Purple teaming and the Cloud. You can never know everything, but knowledge is power; so I always strive to learn something new as often as family, life and work allow.
I am also a motorcyclist and boulderer when not chasing around after 2 kids and my darling wife.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Study List</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/study/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/study/</guid>
      <description>The home of my collected learning; past, present and future. Here I document the courses &amp;amp; certifications, blogs, books and other resources I have used since I got onto the Cyber Security path
 Courses (upcoming and in Progress)  Certified Kubernetes Adminstrator - Time to learn how to use this tech properly before I can secure it.  Completed Sites  Pentester Academy - Always striving to improve my skills, I am using the content here to supplement my other training.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/resources/</guid>
      <description> Pages Just some links to pages I have found useful across the internet.
 PentesterAcademy HackTheBox The Many Hats Club Blackroomsec 0x00sec Pentesterlabs Hacksplaining BrightTalk Azeria Labs CodeArcana Radare2 Gitbook Cheatography   Github Repos Useful Repos from Github
 Awesome Hacking Reverse Engineering Ninja Admins Awesome CyberSkills [Ropper](sashs / Ropper) JohnTheRipper  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>