<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris Clarkson</title>
    <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chris Clarkson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 12:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://chrisclarkson.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Relaunch</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/posts/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/posts/first/</guid>
      <description>And so, With the help of Hugo the site has been relaunched.
Look out for posts on:
 Hacking The Cloud Reverse Engineering Coding Hardware Drones  There will also be the odd post about Climbing, Motorcycles and other goings on too</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Chris. I am a Hacker, Developer and Geek. I have a passion for all things Cyber Security, but my main areas of focus are in Hardware &amp;ldquo;hacking&amp;rdquo; (making and breaking) and the Cloud. You can never know everything, but knowledge is power; so I always strive to learn something new as often as family, work and life allow.
I am also a motorcyclist and boulderer when not chasing around after 2 kids and my darling wife.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/projects/</guid>
      <description>Things I am working on at the moment&amp;hellip;
CyberSecLab - Terraform, Ansible and Python scripts for an offensive security lab in AWS
Inspired by Rob and his Shiva project to automatically create an attack ready ubuntu host, I decided to expand on the concept and automate the deployment of not only an attack host, but an environment where you can perform all manner of cyber-sec activities from anywhere you choose has an internet connection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/resources/</guid>
      <description> Pages Just some links to pages I have found useful across the internet.
 PentesterAcademy HackTheBox The Many Hats Club Blackroomsec 0x00sec Pentesterlabs Hacksplaining BrightTalk Azeria Labs CodeArcana Radare2 Gitbook Cheatography  Github Repos Useful Repos from Github
 Awesome Hacking Reverse Engineering Ninja Admins Awesome CyberSkills Ropper JohnTheRipper  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Study List</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/study/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/study/</guid>
      <description>Past and Present
Courses  Penetration Testing With Kali  The precursor course to the OSCP examination. Its very difficult to put into words how much I have learned from this course so far, and there is always more to learn #TryHarder.  CISSP (Completed)  The Gold standard for information security professionals, I would advise anybody working in IT Security to do this course. Its benefit lies in understanding, as a techie I gained a deeper understanding and appreciation of how the Policy and process side of Security works.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>