My name is Kara Zor-El.
24 years ago my planet, Krypton,
was in serious peril.
My cousin, Kal-El,
was sent to a planet called Earth
for his own safety and protection.
You may know his story.
The story you don't know is
that I was sent to protect him.
Your pod's coordinates are
interlocked with Kal-El's.
- You will follow him to Earth.
- I'm not afraid, Father.
The trip is long but
you'll sleep most of the way
and we'll be with you in your dreams.
You'll journey to Earth to look
after your baby cousin, Kal-El.
Because of the Earth's yellow sun,
you'll have great powers on this planet.
You will do extraordinary things.
I won't fail Kal-El or you.
I love you, Kara.
You must go, now.
Go!
Things didn't exactly go
according to my mother's plan.
Krypton's destruction sent a shock wave
that knocked my pod off course
and into the Phantom Zone.
A region in space where time doesn't pass.
I slept there for 24 years...
until somehow I got here.
When I arrived, I was
still a 13-year-old girl.
But in that same time my
cousin Kal-El had grown up
and revealed himself to your world...
as Superman.
The most powerful man in the universe.
My cousin wanted me to
have the same safe...
human-type of childhood he did.
So he placed me with my
adoptive family, the Danvers.
Scientists who once helped him
understand his own super abilities.
I know I'm not your mom, sweetheart.
But you're safe here.
They had a daughter, Alex.
And despite being born
on different planets,
we both shared one thing:
we knew our lives would
never be the same again.
My cousin... he didn't need my protection.
I didn't have a mission anymore.
But even though I had all
the same powers he did...
Sorry, sorry.
I decided the best thing
I could do is fit in.
After all...
Earth didn't need another hero.
I need two tickets in the
Orchestra section for Wicked.
No, not for Ms. Grant,
her mother wants to see it.
Yes, again. Sure, I'll hold.
Charlie?
I'm calling about the
Correspondent's dinner,
I need to make sure Ms. Grant doesn't
end up next to Bill O'Riley again.
I work at CatCo Worldwide Media.
An online and print empire
built by my boss, Cat Grant.
The most powerful woman in National City.
At least... for the next few days.
Did you see this? There was an
armored car robbery last night.
There were no witnesses
except for this homeless guy
who swears the perp had horns.
Like... on his head!
I'm telling you, they're out there: aliens!
Winn, there's no such thing as aliens.
Well, you might feel different
if you read this website.
- You write that website.
- I... I contribute.
Hey, um, I was wondering
if maybe you wanna...
I don't know, go see a movie tonight.
I... I can't. I'm sorry.
I have a date.
- Date, really?
- Uhm.
That's great... fun. Dating is fun.
- Who... who is that with?
- It's an online date.
Says we are 82% compatible, so...
should be good.
You know that you can't quantify
emotions based on an algorithm?
Winn, you are IT, isn't your
whole life based on algorithms?
Yes, so if there was an algorithm for
love I think that I would know about it.
It's just that... you're gonna
know when it hits you, Kara.
It'll be all: "pa-pow".
Ugh, this elevator is a human petri dish,
it's like standing up in coach.
- She's here.
- How do you do that?
Good morning, Ms. Grant.
The only reason I bought this building
was because it had a private elevator.
That way, I don't have to get soaked
in cheap cologne every morning,
getting to my office, find out who used it,
have them reprimanded, or
bathed, I don't care which...
Here's your latte. Hot.
That would be new and different.
I have a meeting with
the Board today at lunch,
so cancel sushi with my mother.
Oh, and cancel my therapist.
I won't be needing it if I'm
not having lunch with my mother.
Got it.
Also...
I've emailed a list.
Prepare termination letters for
the Tribune employees as noted.
I realise that there are quite a few.
But it would be so nice
if you handwrote them.
Use the lesser card stock.
You're downsizing the Tribune?
But that was your first acquisition.
Go see if the new art
director has the layout ready.
It's not that I don't see your frown,
it's just that I don't care
enough to ask why it's there.
All those people... they're
going to lose their jobs.
What's going to happen to
them, to their families?
They don't have to downsize
at the Daily Planet.
Metropolis has a person who wears a cape...
and flies around performing heroic acts.
The Planet puts this
superlative man on their cover
54% of the time.
You wanna save the Trib'?
Go find me a hero, Kira.
Kara.
Hello?
- Hello?
- I'll be just a minute.
Ms. Grant sent me for layouts
and she doesn't like to wait.
She can wait a minute.
Have you met Ms. Grant?
Yeah, what is she gonna do?
Fire me right after hiring me?
Her loss.
Hey.
I'm the new guy.
Oh, it's him!
I've seen this picture
like a million times.
It won the Pulitzer.
- Wow.
- Yeah...
Only 'cause it was the
first real shot of him.
Little secret: he actually posed for that.
I guess he likes me.
Oh, my God, you're Jimmy Olson.
The photographer from the Daily Planet.
James Olson.
Well, Jimmy is reserved
for my mom and the big guy.
He's kind of stuck in his ways.
Uhm, I know what I've read, but...
What's he like in real life?
He is
everything you wanted to be and more.
I was scared to move out here,
but he told me the biggest
risk is never taking any, so...
- Take it.
- Uhm?
- This? Really? Oh God, no, I can't.
- I can't...
- It's just a print. Please, take it.
But first you have to tell me who you are.
- I never got your name.
- Oh...
Gosh... Hi.
Kara.
Kara Danvers.
Kara...
Anyone ever tell you that you look
a little like him right here?
No.
No, no you're the first.
- Thank you very much.
- Yeah, of course.
Uhm...
Layouts.
Right.
Almost forgot them.
Bye.
"Pa-pow".
I have a conference in Geneva and
I need to be on a plane in 2 hours.
And I have a blind date in half an hour
and I need you to help
me pick out what to wear.
- I win.
- Why do you do this to me?
'Cause I'm your sister and you love me.
I don't know, I feel like I'm
not living up to my potential.
I went to work for Cat Grant
because I thought
working in a media company
run by a powerful woman who
actually shapes the way people think
would be the way that I could
make a difference, but...
instead I just
fetch layouts and coffee.
You always wanted to be normal, right?
So, having a crappy boss and
absolutely nothing to wear...
- This is what normal looks like.
- I am not normal!
I have the same powers he does.
I can lift a bus, stop a bullet,
Alex, I can fly!
At least I think I can, I
haven't done it in years.
Kara...
You've got a good job,
you're cute,
and thanks to your alien DNA
you can't get pimples.
Life is not so bad.
But, if you really wanna help somebody,
you'll pick between one of these
two so I can get on my plane.
- Yep.
- Good choice.
When in doubt, go with
blue, it is your color.
All right...
Text me every detail from your date
and I will call you when
I'm back from Geneva.
- I love you.
- Love you.
So, where are you from originally?
Like where was I born?
Uhm, north.
I gotta hit this back real quick.
Check please.
Make sure your number is on it.
- If you're just joining us...
- Turn that up!
National City Airlines
flight 237, bound for Geneva,
is experiencing some loss of altitude.
The pilot seems to be circling the
city after apparent engine failure.
Did he say Geneva? Alex.
We just lost another engine.
Mayday, mayday, mayday.
We are going down. I
repeat, we are going down.
Flight attendants, brace for impact.
We're leveling off.
Oh, come on!
transcribed and synced by AJ
The passengers of flight 237
appear to have a guardian angel
when what many report to
be a female flying form
rescued them from certain death.
Lena Winn is live at the scene.
Thank you, Rick. Guardian
angel or human wrecking ball?
- What?
- There is destruction all over Otto Binder Bridge.
And one quick...
Well, you try saving a plane for the
first time. See if you don't make a mess.
Oh, my God.
I know!
It's incredible!
Oh, sorry. That was too hard.
I'm just... I'm so excited.
- I still can't believe I did it.
- Yeah.
Neither can I. Are you okay?
Me? Am I okay? Are you okay?
- Yes, thank you.
- Were you scared?
I mean, I was scared too, but
you... You had to be terrified.
Because you had no idea
I was coming to save you.
- I need a drink.
- Right! Yeah, we need to celebrate.
It has been so long... I
almost forgot how to fly.
Well, not so much "how", but more...
more how it feels, like...
scared, but good scared.
Like... like that moment right before
you kiss someone for the first time.
And now... now it's like...
I'm not sure what comes next.
Or maybe I am sure and I'm
just afraid of what it means...
- and if it means what I think it means.
- What were you thinking?
You exposed yourself.
To the world.
You're out there now, Kara.
Everyone will know about you
and you can't take that back.
I don't want to.
This is what I was talking about, Alex.
I've always felt the need to help people,
and tonight I finally got that chance.
I didn't travel 2.000 light
years just to be an assistant.
What if people figure out who you are?
What you are?
It's just...
_
It's not safe
for you to do anything like that.
Ever again.
I'm kind of tired, I just...
carried a plane on my
back. I'm gonna go to bed.
You should go.
Don't say I didn't warn you.
Good morning, National City. Our top story,
the only story anyone's talking about:
who is the mystery flying
woman who saved the plane?
Despite extensive efforts,
no one has been able to identify
who or rather what she is.
Oh, my God, Kara. You're a life saver.
Thanks for doing those comps for
me. Cat said I did great work.
Oh, sure, Hayashi. No big deal.
Her timing, seriously, she is...
- Pretty cool, huh?
- A plane-saving lady?
How is the world supposed to take you
seriously if you can't even come up with a suit?
Metropolis gets him and
what does National City get?
Some rookie superhero?
- _
- I know many of you...
are used to being second best
but it's new to me.
The most incredible event in
the history of National City
and yet we have no exclusive of any kind.
We don't have much to go on.
The image we're working off is low res.
I guess she's around 5'9''.
It's tough to gauge with her
height measured against an airplane.
Hair color brown. Or... black.
Or maybe her hair is just dirty.
You know, from soot.
- The plane exhaust.
- James, you make an excellent point.
Do you think there's any
connection between this hero
- and...
- To my friend in blue?
I don't know. I mean, not
that he mentioned, but...
if she's anything like him,
she's a hero.
Saving people's what they're
born to do. She'll be back.
She better be.
This girl is the answer.
She is exactly what I
need to save the Tribune.
Besides fatty foods, there is
nothing people love more than a hero.
We are going to blow her up.
We will feature her
online and in the paper,
but we need images,
we need video, we need an interview,
an exclusive content. So go.
Go get me that girl.
And Kara...
Go get me a lettuce wrap.
It's funny. That was
the first thing he did.
Save a plane, I mean.
Winn, I need to talk to you on the roof.
The roof?
Kara?
Hey, uh, just whatever you have
to say, can you make it quick?
I'm not really into being this high up.
Okay, uhm... Winn...
I'm going to tell you something about me
that only three people in my life know.
Can I trust you?
- Yeah, yeah, of course.
- Good.
I just... really want
someone to be excited for me.
And I, uhm...
Right, how do...
There's something about me...
that for most of my life, I've ran from it.
But last night I embraced who
I am and I don't wanna stop.
Oh, my God, you're a lesbian.
Oh, Kara, that is why you're not into me.
- This is... this is great news!
- No. I'm not gay!
I am...
I'm her!
The woman who saved the plane!
Okay.
Yeah, okay. Right.
Kara, what are you doing? Hey, Kara!
Hey, get away from the
ledge, you're gonna get hurt.
Kara! Hey!
You're... you're her!
Yep.
More reports coming in to
last night's plane rescue.
The big question: is there a connection
between this mysterious flying woman...
- More coffee.
- ...and the Man of Steel?
- Hey!
- Sorry about that, sir.
Can you believe it? A female hero.
Nice for my daughter to have
someone like that to look up to.
Yeah, real nice.
What happened with the plane, Vartox?
You were ordered to bring it down.
Our trap worked.
The DEO agents were on
board and the bomb detonated.
- Then why aren't they dead?
- The female...
She flew into the sky and caught the plane.
Who is she?
Jor-El saved his child
before Krypton's destruction.
- Alura's daughter.
- She's working with the humans.
12 years.
We've been forced to hide in the shadows.
But the General's arrival is
imminent. Nothing must interfere.
You are instructed to continue your
orders to eliminate the human operatives.
- You can add this girl to the list.
- Can't promise her death won't be public.
- And messy.
- Human casualties are irrelevant.
Good.
And if she is Alura's Zar-El's daughter...
then she will pay for her mother's debts.
And so will her city.
So, how is it? Huh? How does it fit?
I'm not flying around
saving people in this thing.
I... I wouldn't even wear it
to the beach. Where's my cape?
Capes are lame. You can tell your cousin
I said so. Actually, never, never do that.
You look really pretty
without your glasses.
- Winn...
- So...
To be a superhero you need a crime.
I hacked into the NCPD.
There's a car chase on the 112 freeway.
I can do a car chase!
A cape aids with aerodynamics,
I should have thought of that.
West National City Bank
reporting a 432 at 6th and Spring.
- Suspects are armed and dangerous.
- You, uh, you're sure you're bulletproof?
Hope so.
All right, the new cape is made
from a structured polymer composites,
much sturdier than...
And...
This one has the "S".
For "Super", just like your cousin.
It's not an "S".
It's my family's coat of arms.
The House of El.
***
I'm assuming you can't catch on fire.
Made of low grade Kryptonite.
Radioactive mineral from your home planet.
- It weakens you.
- Where... where am I?
- Who are you?
- My name is Hank Henshaw.
And I believe you already know
Agent Danvers.
She doesn't need this.
Welcome to the DEO,
the Department of Extranormal Operations.
The DEO monitors and protects Earth
from extraterrestrial presence and or...
invasion.
That means you.
Your ship.
We keep it here as a reminder
of the day you crashed on Earth.
You are the reason for all of this.
Me? But...
My... But my cousin was here
two dozen years before me.
And it was his arrival that triggered
the need for this organization.
We realised we weren't
alone in the universe
and we might soon be getting more...
immigrants.
Sure enough, you came along.
And with you...
Fort Rozz.
Fort Rozz?
Krypton's Maximum Security prison.
Banished at the Phantom Zone,
same place your ship got stuck,
but just like yours it didn't stay there.
We're not sure how your pod got loose.
What we do know is this:
you pulled Fort Rozz with you.
When it crashed,
the alien convicts...
the worst criminals in the
galaxy, they all escaped.
And you brought them here.
This beings...
Some of them have powers
from your darkest nightmares.
For over a decade they've stayed hidden.
But in the last year
many have been emerging...
making themselves known.
They're planning something.
We're just not sure what it is yet.
Your plane.
That wasn't an accident.
They were trying to kill you.
I can help you stop them.
How? You couldn't even
stop us from capturing you.
I... I'm still learning.
Our job is keeping people in the
dark about alien life on Earth,
and nothing says "covert operation"
like a flying woman in a red skirt.
They know about my cousin,
they don't fear him.
Plenty of people do, just
not popular to admit it.
You wanna help?
Go back to getting someone's coffee.
I know you're mad and you're hurt.
I wanted to tell you every single day...
Instead, you told me every single
day not to be who I really am.
- You have to listen to me.
- I can't!
This just kind of feels like
one big coincidence, doesn't it?
You working here, hunting
down aliens, me being one?
I can't help but think
the real reason that you were
recruited was because of me.
They recruited me because my
background in bioengineering
makes me an expert in alien physiology.
And, yeah,
it helps that I shared a bathroom with one.
I'm leaving now.
Unless you wanna try and stop me.
Which I wouldn't.
I know you don't wanna hear this,
Agent Danvers, but she's dangerous.
You above all people should know that.
Of course leave it to media magnate
Cat Grant to put a name to her face.
Ms. Grant dubbed National City's
new female here "Supergirl".
And if Twitter is any indicator,
the name appears to be catching...
"Supergirl"?
We can't name her that!
"We" didn't.
Right, I'm...
sorry. It's just...
I don't want to minimize
the importance of this.
A female superhero,
shouldn't she be called Superwoman?
I'm sorry, darling, I just can't hear you
over the loud color of your cheap pants.
If we call her "Supergirl",
something less than what she is,
doesn't that make us
guilty of being anti-feminist?
Didn't you say she was a hero?
I'm the hero.
I stuck a label on the side
of this girl, I branded her.
She will forever be linked
to CatCo, to the Tribune...
to me.
And...
what do you this is so bad about "girl"?
I'm a girl.
And your boss,
and powerful, and rich and hot and smart.
So if you perceive "Supergirl"
as anything less than excellent,
isn't the real problem you?
And if you're so smart, Kara,
could you please give me one
reason why I shouldn't fire you?
I printed it.
And it's an even higher
resolution than you hoped for.
James...
You are interrupting
a very craftily worded termination.
Kara wanted to surprise you,
but she had to tell her friend
that works at West National City Bank.
- The branch that got robbed.
- Right!
Right, yes, I went there.
You know, it took me a while
to park my car in the...
streets. The one-way
streets are so confusing.
You tell it so much better...
Kara convinced her source to allow us
to use a photograph that she captured.
You got a clean image of Supergirl?
Kara,
if you can't take credit
when you do something well,
you are gonna be at the
bottom of the pile forever.
But mazel tov.
You bought yourself another day.
- I was handling the situation.
- Oh, yeah? What was your plan?
To get yelled at and fired?
'Cause that was working.
I don't need you or anyone
else fighting my battles for me.
I'm communicating at 50,000 Hz.
- If you can hear this,
- You okay?
you were not born on this Earth.
Yeah, I... I have a
headache. I need some water.
Painful, isn't it?
The humans of National City will suffer
ten times this pain if you don't face me.
Meet me at the National City power plant.
How many innocent people are going to die
until you prove that you are not a coward?
Daughter of Alura.
Clever. Picking a spot lined with led.
But I can still hear your heart beat.
On my planet, females bow before males.
- This is not your planet.
- You look like Alura.
How do you know my mother's name?
You don't easily forget the name of
the woman who condemned you to prison.
Fort Rozz?
- What does that have to do with her?
- She was our judge.
And jailer.
Can't kill her...
so killing you will have to do.
Just because you wear that symbol in
your chest doesn't mean you're him.
Fighting him would be an honor.
Fighting you is just exercise.
You actually think that you could stop me?
That you'd be able to stop any of us?
Now you know what is like to bleed.
Soon, your whole city will bleed.
- ***-1, pursue the hostile.
- Copy that.
Hey, hey, I'm here. I got you, I got you.
- You're gonna be okay.
- I never felt pain like that before.
I never felt pain.
You're not indestructible, Kara.
Nice move nearly letting
that alien cut you in half.
If we can ID his weapon, it
might give us a way to defeat him.
Look at that...
You did help.
Did you know about my mom?
That she was the one who
locked up all those aliens?
It's why I didn't want you going out there.
Showing yourself,
showing this.
The Fort Rozz escapees would give anything
to get revenge on your mother and the
only way that they can do that now...
is to hurt you.
I'm trying to protect you.
You were right.
The world doesn't need me.
Kara, it's me.
Can we talk?
I know you can see me.
I know what you're thinking.
That this is all your fault.
But it's not.
Before you came to live with us...
I was the star.
And then, I mean...
How could I compete with you?
With someone
who could touch the stars?
And I was happy when you decided not to use
your powers. You know, you...
feeling like less somehow...
made me feel like more.
Now...
The world needs you to fly, Kara.
I can't, Alex.
- I can't do it.
- Yeah, you can.
- Your family believes in you.
- I know you do.
Oh, I don't mean me.
- That's Kryptonese writing.
- Yeah.
Hank and his old team recovered it
from the pod that brought you to Earth.
- Mom.
- Kara, my brave daughter.
By now you have become the woman
I knew you would grow up to be.
And though you were sent to
Earth to protect young Kal-El,
your destiny is not tied to his.
There is no correct path in life.
You will lose your way many times.
What's important
is that you find your way back
to the brave girl you always were.
Be wise,
be strong...
and always be true to yourself.
So, what do we do now?
First thing first.
You need to change.
It's Agent Danvers and her
sister from another planet.
- She's here to help us fight Vartox.
- I told you I don't trust aliens.
There's no one I trust more.
Like her cousin, she was
sent here too, to help us.
And if you want anymore of my help,
- we're gonna let her.
- I found Vartox.
Sir, ma'ams...
Where?
The sliver of metal you
extracted from Supergirl's arm.
Vartox's axe has a unique nuclear thumbprint.
Satellites picked him up
heading towards the city.
Vartox said he was ready
to start killing humans.
- Looks like tonight's the night.
- Order strike team to intercept.
- Your men will not be able to stop him.
- Thank you for your opinion, Ms. Danvers.
Director Henshaw...
People of this city will die
because of something I did.
I started this.
You have to let me stop it.
Make sure you win.
Do you have eyes on the target?
I got him.
You never should have come back for war.
She's not strong enough.
Why? Because she's just a girl?
It's exactly what we were counting on.
I analyzed the metal on the axe.
It's powered by a
self-generating atomic charge
reaching temperatures up to 2500 degrees.
- How does that help?
- If it gets any hotter than that...
it's gonna explode.
She just has to get close
enough to do her thing.
Stop... I give up.
- I don't wanna die.
- Give your mother my regards.
Kara, do it now.
It's not working. I can't do it!
It's why you were sent here.
I believe that now, you
have to believe it too.
It's over.
You think I'm the threat?
You have no idea what's coming.
She followed your orders. She won.
Yeah. The first time.
Director Henshaw...
I wasn't only recruited
because of my sister, was I?
Yeah, she's why you got in.
You are why you get to stay.
If... If I believe that
comments on the website,
they mentioned a "female/reptilian
boxing match in the desert".
I'll tell you all about it
at our next crime-fighting lunch hour.
- Wait, so the super friends are back?
- We're not calling ourselves that.
James.
- Do you have time to grab lunch?
- You must be hungry.
Probably burned a lot of calories
fighting an axe-wielding alien.
Meet me on the roof.
You knew?
This whole time?
He told you?
Well, he knew that I was trying
to expand my own horizons,
so, as a favor, he asked me to
expand them here, National City.
Hang out.
Be near you.
So, wait a minute. He...
He wanted me to do this?
Why didn't he just tell me?
Because he wanted you to
choose it for yourself.
The same way he did.
That's what makes a hero, Kara.
Here.
From him.
It's the blanket he was
wrapped in when he was a baby.
Apparently this cape won't shred.
Thank you.
He's really proud of you.
Me too.
Now, don't you have a city to protect?
You know... up, up and away?
I was sent here to protect my cousin.
Turns out he didn't need my protection.
But there's a whole planet
full of people who do.
Earth doesn't have just one hero anymore.
Now it has me.
Now it has Supergirl.
General, Vartox is dead.
He chose death over capture.
- Typical of his race.
- He did accomplish one thing.
The identity of the girl.
It seems... she is Alura's daughter.
My dear little niece.
Of course.
She escaped with her cousin.
A much less of a threat
than he is to our endeavors.
You're wrong.
If she's anything like her mother,
she will just as formidable.
It was my right
to lead Krypton, I will lead Earth.
We all will.
Find her and kill her.
Are you certain, General?
After all...
Kara Zor-El is your blood.
No one can be allowed to stand against us.
Not even my niece.
transcribed and synced by AJ
www.tvsubtitles.net