<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Courses on Chris Clarkson</title>
    <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/categories/courses/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Courses on Chris Clarkson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:30:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://chrisclarkson.org/categories/courses/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CCSP</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/ccsp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/ccsp/</guid>
      <description>The Gold standard for Cloud security professionals, I would advise anybody working in Cloud Security to do this course. Its benefit lies in understanding, as a techie I gained a deeper understanding and appreciation of how the Policy and process side of Cloud Security works.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CISSP</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/cissp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:30:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/cissp/</guid>
      <description>The Gold standard for information security professionals, I would advise anybody working in IT Security to do this course. Its benefit lies in understanding, as a techie I gained a deeper understanding and appreciation of how the Policy and process side of Security works.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AWS Solutions Architect - Professional</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/awssolpro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:25:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/awssolpro/</guid>
      <description>Obtained a much deeper understanding of AWS and especially its capabilities and limitations with respect to securing cloud workloads. A much deeper dive into the services offered by AWS and how a broad collection of those services come together to form solution stacks. It also provides the students with much needed detail on migrating workloads to the cloud, where there is still high demand at present with regards to cloud projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AWS Solutions Architect - Associate</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/awssolassoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:20:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/awssolassoc/</guid>
      <description>Excellent course to learn the intricacies of AWS and round out the knowledge gained on the Job. Using AWS day to day for a number of years on mainly development oriented projects its easy to overlook the more infrastructure targeted services. This course gives an understanding of those offerings and places them in context to aid in their understanding.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CEH - Certified Ethical Hacker</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/ceh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:15:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/ceh/</guid>
      <description>An excellent introduction to the ways a hacker works to compromise a system. Despite it being widely disparaged by the Cybersecurity community, I found it to be insightful and good all-round introductory course. There are some questions around the dubious title and the format of the exam, but content is valid and useful especially for someone without a background in offensive security.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CHFI - Certified Hacking Forensics Investigator</title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/chfi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 09:10:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/chfi/</guid>
      <description>A very insightful course into art of computer forensics and the techniques that are used to catch hackers. Very interesting to take the knowledge gained here and work out ways to evade them, excellent course to take that stage further and develop the adversarial mindset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 16:52:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisclarkson.org/courses/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>