<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>design-comparable SMD | James E. Pustejovsky</title>
    <link>/tags/design-comparable-smd/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/design-comparable-smd/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>design-comparable SMD</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>design-comparable SMD</title>
      <link>/tags/design-comparable-smd/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between-case standardized effect size analysis of single case design: Examination of the two methods</title>
      <link>/publication/bcsmd-examination-of-two-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bcsmd-examination-of-two-methods/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A meta-analysis of school-based group contingency interventions for students with challenging behavior: An update</title>
      <link>/publication/school-based-group-contingencies-meta-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/school-based-group-contingencies-meta-analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A meta-analysis of technology-aided instruction and intervention for students with ASD</title>
      <link>/publication/taii-meta-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/taii-meta-analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional assessment-based interventions for students with or at-risk for high incidence disabilities: Field-testing single-case synthesis methods</title>
      <link>/publication/fabi-meta-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/fabi-meta-analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research synthesis and meta-analysis of single-case designs</title>
      <link>/publication/meta-analysis-of-scd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/meta-analysis-of-scd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between-case standardized mean difference effect sizes for single-case designs: A primer and tutorial using the scdhlm web application</title>
      <link>/publication/bc-smd-primer-and-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bc-smd-primer-and-tutorial/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New tutorial paper on BC-SMD effect sizes</title>
      <link>/scdhlm-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/scdhlm-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to announce that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.campbellcollaboration.org/&#34;&gt;Campbell Collaboration&lt;/a&gt; has just published a new discussion paper that I wrote with my colleagues Jeff Valentine and Emily Tanner-Smith about &lt;a href=&#34;https://campbellcollaboration.org/library/effect-sizes-single-case-designs-campbell-discussion-paper-1.html&#34;&gt;between-case standardized mean difference effect sizes for single-case designs&lt;/a&gt;.
The paper provides a relatively non-technical introduction to BC-SMD effect sizes and a tutorial on how to use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jepusto.shinyapps.io/scdhlm/&#34;&gt;scdhlm web-app&lt;/a&gt; for calculating estimates of the BC-SMD for user-provided data.
If you have any questions or feedback about the app, please feel free to contact me!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>scdhlm</title>
      <link>/software/scdhlm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/software/scdhlm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;An R package implementing several methods of estimating a design-comparable standardized mean difference effect size based on data from a single-case design. Methods include those from Hedges, Pustejovsky, &amp;amp; Shadish (
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/SMD-for-SCD&#34;&gt;2012&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/SMD-for-MBD&#34;&gt;2013&lt;/a&gt;) and 
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/design-comparable-effect-sizes/&#34;&gt;Pustejovsky, Hedges, &amp;amp; Shadish (2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=scdhlm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Available on the Comprehensive R Archive Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/getting-started-with-scdhlm&#34;&gt;Installation instructions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jepusto/scdhlm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Source code on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://jepusto.shinyapps.io/scdhlm/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;scdhlm&lt;/a&gt;: An interactive web application for calculating design-comparable standardized mean difference effect sizes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting started with scdhlm</title>
      <link>/getting-started-with-scdhlm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/getting-started-with-scdhlm/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATED 10/2/2016 after posting the package to CRAN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are step-by-step instructions on how to download and install the scdhlm package for R. You’ll need to have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://cran.us.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;copy of R installed&lt;/a&gt;. There are two ways to do the installation: through the Comprehensive R Archive Network (CRAN) or from the source code on Github. I describe each approach in turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;option-1-via-cran&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Option 1: Via CRAN&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go via CRAN to install the most recent stable version of the package. Type the following commands at the R prompt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;scdhlm&amp;quot;)
library(scdhlm)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;option-2-via-github&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Option 2: Via Github&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go via Github to get the latest development version of the package. For this option, you will first need to install the devtools package:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;devtools&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have successfully installed this package, type the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(devtools)
install_github(&amp;quot;jepusto/scdhlm&amp;quot;)
library(scdhlm)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;further-instructions&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Further instructions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll only need to do the installation once. Once you’ve got the package installed, type the following in order to access the package within an R session: &lt;code&gt;library(scdhlm)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To open the package documentation, type &lt;code&gt;package?scdhlm&lt;/code&gt;. To access the documentation for an individual function in this package, just type &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; followed by the name of the function. For instance, one of the main functions in the package is called &lt;code&gt;g_REML&lt;/code&gt;; to access its documentation, type &lt;code&gt;?g_REML&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;web-interface-for-calculating-effect-sizes&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;web-interface for calculating effect sizes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package includes an interactive app (written with &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt;) for calculating design-comparable standardized mean differences. To run this app on your computer, you will first need to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/&#34;&gt;install RStudio&lt;/a&gt; (if you don’t already have it). Then ensure that you have the &lt;code&gt;shiny&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;markdown&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; packages installed by running the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;install.packages(&amp;quot;shiny&amp;quot;)
install.packages(&amp;quot;markdown&amp;quot;)
install.packages(&amp;quot;ggplot2&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, open the app by typing the following at the prompt within RStudio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(scdhlm)
shine_scd()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app should now open in your web browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design-comparable effect sizes in multiple baseline designs: A general modeling framework</title>
      <link>/publication/design-comparable-effect-sizes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/design-comparable-effect-sizes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New article: Design-comparable effect sizes in multiple baseline designs: A general modeling framework</title>
      <link>/design-comparable-effect-sizes-in-multiple-baseline-designs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/design-comparable-effect-sizes-in-multiple-baseline-designs/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;My article with Larry Hedges and Will Shadish, titled “Design-comparable effect sizes in multiple baseline designs: A general modeling framework” has been accepted at Journal of Educational and Behavioral Statistics. The abstract is below. Here’s the article at &lt;a href=&#34;http://doi.org/10.3102/1076998614547577&#34;&gt;the journal website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;/files/Effect-sizes-in-multiple-baseline-designs-JEBS.pdf&#34;&gt;Postprint&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;/files/Effect-sizes-in-multiple-baseline-designs-Simulation-results.pdf&#34;&gt;supporting materials&lt;/a&gt; are available. An R package that implements the proposed methods is &lt;a href=&#34;/getting-started-with-scdhlm/&#34;&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In single-case research, the multiple baseline design is a widely used approach for evaluating the effects of interventions on individuals. Multiple baseline designs involve repeated measurement of outcomes over time and the controlled introduction of a treatment at different times for different individuals. This article outlines a general approach for defining effect sizes in multiple baseline designs that are directly comparable to the standardized mean difference from a between-subjects randomized experiment. The target, design-comparable effect size parameter can be estimated using restricted maximum likelihood together with a small-sample correction analogous to Hedges’ g. The approach is demonstrated using hierarchical linear models that include baseline time trends and treatment-by-time interactions. A simulation compares the performance of the proposed estimator to that of an alternative, and an application illustrates the model-fitting process.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing single-case designs: d, G, hierarchical models, Bayesian estimators, generalized additive models, and the hopes and fears of researchers about analyses</title>
      <link>/publication/analyzing-scd-hopes-and-fears/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/analyzing-scd-hopes-and-fears/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis and meta-analysis of single-case designs with a standardized mean difference statistic: A primer and applications</title>
      <link>/publication/bc-smd-primer-and-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bc-smd-primer-and-applications/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A standardized mean difference effect size for multiple baseline designs</title>
      <link>/publication/smd-for-mbd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/smd-for-mbd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A d-statistic for single-case designs that is equivalent to the usual between-groups d-statistics</title>
      <link>/publication/between-groups-d-statistic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/between-groups-d-statistic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operationally comparable effect sizes for meta-analysis of single-case research</title>
      <link>/publication/operationally-comparable-effect-sizes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/operationally-comparable-effect-sizes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This thesis studies quantitative methods for summarizing and synthesizing single-case studies, a class of research designs for evaluating the effects of interventions through repeated measurement of individuals. Despite long-standing interest in meta-analytic synthesis of single-case research, there remains a lack of consensus about appropriate methods, even about the most basic question of what effect size metrics are useful and appropriate. I argue that operational comparability, or invariance to heterogeneous operational procedures, is crucial property for an effect size metric. I then consider two problems with operational comparability that arise in single-case research. The first problem is to find effect sizes that can be applied across studies that use different research designs, such as single-case designs and two-group randomized experiments. The second problem is to find effect sizes that can be applied across studies that use varied operations for measuring the same construct. To address each of these problems, I propose structural models that capture essential features of multiple relevant operations (either design-related operations or measurement-related operations). I then use these structural models to precisely define target effect size parameters and to consider identification issues and estimation strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1 defines operational comparability and situates the concept within the broad methodological concerns of meta-analysis, then reviews relevant features of single-case research and previously proposed effect sizes. Chapter 2 describes an abstract set of modeling criteria for constructing design-comparable effect sizes. Chapters 3 applies the general criteria to the case of standardized mean differences and proposes an effect size estimator based on restricted maximum likelihood. Chapter 4 presents several applications of the proposed models and methods. Chapter 5 proposes measurement-comparability model and defines effect size measures for use in studies of free-operant behavior, one of the most common classes of outcomes in single-case research. Chapter 6 extends the proposed effect size models to incorporate more complex features, including time trends and serial dependence, and studies a method of estimating those models through a combination of marginal quasi-likelihood and Gaussian pseudo-likelihood estimating equations. Chapter 7 collects various further extensions, areas for further research, and concluding thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A standardized mean difference effect size for single case designs</title>
      <link>/publication/smd-for-scd/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/smd-for-scd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
